- Hello and welcome back to Hardware Architecture.
Now you might ask, you know, why do I tell you
about hardware architecture?
You're not, probably you're not gonna build any hardware,
although it's fun stuff to do, and if you're gonna become
a computer scientist, which most of you won't want to be,
it's a great thing to study, and it's a,
those who build our hardware are amazingly talented
individuals, and it's a really rewarding job.
The reason I like talking to you about hardware
is because I want to be able to use words
at some point and say, oh, secondary storage,
or central processing unit, or random access memory,
or peripherals, you know, input devices,
and I want to be able to say those words,
and I want you to be able to understand them.
And so I got, I'll start with a little piece of hardware
called the Raspberry Pi, and the Raspberry Pi
is a cute little single board computer.
As we go forward, these things are smaller
and smaller and smaller, and the interesting thing is
is that the architecture of these stays the same,
but the number of components drops.
So I'm gonna start and give you a block diagram
of sort of a generic computer,
and tell you the major parts of it.
Now, I'm gonna show you some really old hardware,
some really new hardware, and then some hardware
that is of medium age, and the medium age hardware
is probably the easiest one to see.
The architecture is the same, okay, and so,
the basic block diagram is that the brains,
if there are brains in computers, which there really aren't,
the software is the closest thing computers have to brains,
but in hardware, the closest brain a computer has is this,
called a microprocessing unit, or a central processor unit,
and this is designed, you know, three billion times a sec,
three billion times a second, to ask the question,
what do you want me to do next?
And these little pins on the back are our instructions,
like 32 or 64 of these pins, three billion times a second,
we send an instruction into these things.
Now, we can't sit there and talk to it, we can't,
and so the instructions we store
in what's called the main memory,
and this memory is really fast,
and the memory sort of feeds this,
and so every time the CPU needs a new instruction,
it asks the memory where that instruction is,
and so the memory feeds the instruction to the CPU,
the CPU does it, says, give me another instruction,
CPU does it, gives me another instruction,
and that is the basic essence of programming.
This asks what's next, and this is where your program
is stored, or a program you purchased
or came with your hardware, where that's all stored,
and those are your places, and so you end up inside,
your programs end up inside this memory.
So then there's, I mean, and so in software,
you tend to program the CPU, and if you had bought
a desktop computer a number of years back,
it would have this thing called the motherboard,
and the motherboard is called this because it kind of
connects all the components together,
and so if you buy memory by itself, it does nothing,
but it has a place to plug into the motherboard,
and if you buy a microprocessor,
it has a place to plug into the motherboard,
and if you buy a hard drive,
this is a really old hard drive,
it has a place to plug in on the motherboard,
and so the motherboard sort of connects everything together.
The hard drive is secondary storage.
Now, the way, how secondary storage is different
than the main memory, which, there it is,
I gotta un-pile this stuff.
So this main memory is really fast,
but as soon as you turn the power off of this memory,
it sort of vanishes, and so to store files
like word processing files or text files or whatever,
you gotta store it on something
that lasts a little bit longer,
and so that's the purpose of the secondary storage.
It's permanent.
When the power's off, it stores it.
Now, this one here is in such bad shape
that it isn't probably storing anything,
but it's got these little heads,
and it spins around and goes in and out,
and we'll have a video later
that shows you one of these things
that's not quite in as bad a shape.
If you look, this has four different platters
that are all spinning around,
and so this is just using magnetic material
and electronics that sort of magnetize
and demagnetize this stuff,
and if you look at a disc, they're often rated,
physical discs are rated in revolutions per minute,
and that's how many times this thing spins around,
and if you got an old desktop and you hear it spin up,
this is the thing that's spinning,
and it's the place that your operating system lives,
your files live, your applications live
while they're stored and while the computer's turned off,
and then they're loaded into this while they're running,
and then
this CPU takes the data from the main memory
and your program runs at three billion operations per second.
So let's talk a little bit about something
that this is probably from the 1960s or 70s.
This actually has, if you're an electrical person,
it has capacitors, those little silver things are capacitors,
these little colored things are resistors,
and that's more capacitors, and then there's wires,
and wires move everything,
and so when you say this has millions of transistors,
oh wait, that isn't a capacitor, that's a transistor,
that's a transistor, when you say that this here has etched,
and if you look closely at this,
go look at a picture of a microprocessor online,
you will see that it has millions of these,
and so the difference between 1960 and today
is this circuitry of capacitors, resistors,
and transistors has been microized and put onto this.
It's using a photographic process,
and they're tinier and tinier and putting more and more on,
and if you think going from millions of these
to one of these is crazy, the thing that's happening now,
and the reason we have whole computers inside our pocket,
is that everything, all of this, this whole thing,
CPU, memory, everything, all of it connected,
and the storage is being made smaller and smaller,
and so this little single board computer, called a Raspberry Pi,
has one thing in it, and it has the main memory,
and it has the CPU, it has connections for things
like peripherals, like keyboards and stuff,
now it doesn't yet have secondary storage on it,
the secondary storage gets plugged in right here via USB,
and then if you take it one step farther to my phone,
it's got the secondary storage built right in,
and so this picture goes from the size of cabinets
in the old days, all the way down to really tiny,
but at the end of the day, inside it is a highly
sophisticated piece of circuitry that asks for instructions
one at a time, and main memory that holds the instructions
and feeds them, okay?
Central processor does the thinking,
let's take a look here, central processor does the thinking,
it runs the program, it's asking what's next,
it's not really smart, but it's really fast,
and so we compensate for the lack of intelligence
of this thing by us writing really good software
that runs really fast, and so voice recognition
on things like phones is possible because computers
have so much storage and they run so fast,
and the algorithms that do voice recognition
are finally starting to work.
Input devices like keyboards and mice and pens and whatever,
they come in, output devices are like the screens
that we see, the main memory is the fast part
of the computer that stores all the programs,
and the secondary memory is the permanent storage.
Increasingly, secondary memory, do I have any USB sticks
in here, I don't, well, increasingly secondary memory
is flash RAM or static RAM with no moving parts,
and so in a few years you'll not even be able to see
secondary memory with moving parts, but that's okay,
it's still secondary memory, it's still memory that lasts,
and so you and where your place is in here
is you live in the main memory, this is you, you are here,
and so in a sense when the CPU asks the question what next,
it is your job to answer that, and you answer that
by writing Python code, and so your Python code,
you'll write a file in Python code, blah, blah, blah,
blah, and then that Python code sort of gets loaded
into main memory, there's a magic translation process
that happens, and then your code is actually answering
this question three billion times a second,
three billion times a second, you're sitting there,
but this is you, you're really out here,
but you then write a file, and the file's loaded in,
and then the file runs, and that's how things are at,
and that's your place in the world.
Now, what's actually running is not Python code,
there is, as I said, a translation process,
you write a Python file, and then Python itself
translates this into the actual language known by
the microprocessor, which is a series of zeros and ones
called machine language, someday I would love to teach you
a class on machine language, but for now we're gonna teach
you Python, and we're gonna use Python as a crutch,
we don't have to talk machine language, but you could,
if you really wanted to, you could know how to write
machine language, but I assure you, Python is far easier
to learn than machine language, so Python acts
as a translator, translates what you're doing
into machine language, and then the machine language
is what's sent back and forth, but still,
even though it's translated to machine language,
it's you, it is you answering those questions,
and that's what a program is, is you pre-storing
your response to the what next question over and over again.
So here's a couple of videos that you can look at on YouTube
about a CPU, these CPUs, it looks very much like this CPU
that I've got with me, these CPUs run extremely high heat,
when you put this thing, or your computer on your lap
and it starts to heat up, that means it's thinking
really, really hard, and so this is a small little old video
from a long time ago that shows what happens
when you take out the cooling capability of microprocessors
and just how hot they can be, and the other video
that I have is a hard disk, something like this hard disk
that I have, except that it works and they turn the power on.
Some of them last for a few seconds,
some of them last for a few minutes, it's never,
(coughs)
I must be allergic to this hard drive,
or maybe it's 'cause there's dust in this hard drive
and I keep spinning it and I sneeze,
but basically, some of them last for a few seconds,
some of them last for a few minutes,
it's not a good idea to open them up,
but I'm glad somebody opened it up and then did what they did
and then recorded it so we can all enjoy what it is
that they're capable of doing, okay?
So that's a quick introduction to hardware,
mostly so that I can use those words going forward.
Now what we're gonna talk about next is communicating
in the language Python, that is writing code
and putting it into the computer so that that can execute,
okay?
(soft music)